Hi, Rachel.
Hi, Ron.
Good evening, how are you? Hey, how's it going?
Doing well.
Thanks for joining tonight. Let me go ahead and pull up my
slides.
I have one, two, three, four, five sets, so.
But the last two are review.
Okay. Any questions, preliminary questions
before we get started?
Okay.
Quote that I like on the right-hand side there.
Today we're going to, or tonight we're going to, or whenever
you're watching this, we're going to talk about sources of
radiation, human effects, and solar radiation
pressure, and then we're going to talk
about basic radiation physics, more on
radiation, and then I should have put a part four here.
I'm going to do a brief review for the
final
and give you information about that.
Okay. First up
on current events is, whoops, that went too far,
Jason Ansley, and he has provided
me a video. Here it is.
Okay. First, can you all see this?
We can still just only see the slide.
Okay.
I will stop sharing. Thank you for letting me know
that, and share
this one. Okay. Can you see it now?
Now you're good.
Okay, good.
Hello. I'm Jason Ansley, and I'm going to present some
basics on the radiation effects, and then I'm going to go into an example
on the Juno spacecraft.
All right. So radiation in the space environment.
Space contains high-energy ionizing radiation capable of
penetrating spacecraft and interacting with materials, electronics, and
biological tissues.
Radiation can consist of energetic particles,
protons, electrons, neutrons, heavy ions, or it could be
electromagnetic radiation like X-rays and gamma rays.
So why is radiation a concern? So we have this
ionization can alter atoms and molecules.
Energetic particles can displace atoms within a material.
And these interactions can actually damage electronics materials and
even DNA.
Earth's atmosphere and magnetic field provide significant protection on its
surface. We have spacecrafts beyond low orbit that will lose
much of this protection.
Going into some radiation measurements, we have the absorbed dose or rad or gray.
That tells you how much radiation energy was deposited on a
material, but not necessarily how biologically damaging it is.
That would be radiation dose or rem.
The dose equivalent, since there
are different types of radiation would have different biological
effectiveness.
Then we have a flux, particles over centimeter squared seconds.
This shows how rapidly particles pass through a certain
area.
And then fluence, we have particles over centimeter squared, total
accumulated particle exposure.
So where does the space radiation come from?
One of them is galactic cosmic rays.
So this is the continuous background radiation.
These originate outside the solar system and are from remnants from
supernova.
Most of the high-energy protons and atomic nuclei, which
is
difficult to completely shield against.
Then we also have solar energetic particles.
So these are produced during solar activity such as flares
or coronal mass ejections.
These are primarily energetic protons with some
electrons and heavier ions. Usually, these are short duration,
but the radiation levels can rise rapidly during a major solar event.
Then there's also trapped radiation.
So these are charged particles trapped by a planetary's magnetic field.
So Earth's Van Allen belts contain
energetic electrons and protons.
The radiation exposure would depend on the spacecraft's
orbit.
You can see on that image on the right, it shows you where
the intensity of the radiation in those Van Allen belts
are. On the left it shows the energy
of the protons, and then on the left is the electrons.
So radiation effects on electronics.
So, there's three major cases. We have total ionizing
dose, displacement damage, and single event effects.
So total ionizing dose, is the total ionizing energy
deposited on a material. So this can cause threshold voltage
shifts, timing changes, part degradation.
There's also displacement damage.
A high energy particle collides with
atoms in a material, and you can move them from their lattice positions.
So this affects solar cells, diodes, optoelectronics, and
semiconductors. We're going to get a little bit into this in the Juno
case.
So there's also single event effects, like single event upsets,
single event latch ups. So single event upsets basically can
cause a bit flip,
and then single event latch ups can create an unwanted current condition,
and that current can possibly damage a component.
And there's other single event effects as well, like single event transient and
single event burnouts.
And then how do we protect against this?
So some considerations.
Use a, or shield these sensitive electronics.
So place a structure of some sort between the sensitive electronics
and then the radiation environment. So have it in enclosure.
Then get, select some appropriate components.
So from, there's radiation tolerant and radiation hardened electronic
components to use from.
And then also, design for error. So include redundancy,
automatic resets, safe mode, some current limiting, and
recovery algorithms all into the design.
All right.
So going away from Earth to Jupiter.
Jupiter also has a strong magnetic field that traps a large amount
of energetic charged particles. So just like the Van Allen
radiation belts for Earth.
So the graph below kind of shows you where those
high energy radiations are in Jupiter, shows the
electrons and protons. And then on the right-hand side, it
compares
Earth's and Jupiter's flux spectra.
So one interesting to note, at Earth,
the proton environment actually dominates at that higher
energy, compared to Jupiter, which that higher energy
is electrons.
Hmm.
Okay. So going to the spacecraft, Juno.
It entered orbit around Jupiter around July 2016.
Its mission was to investigate the planet's structure, the atmosphere, the magnetic
field, and its overall origin.
Most of Juno's sensitive electronics were enclosed within
this one centimeter thick titanium case that would shield it
from the radiation environment. However,
their sensors, like the JunoCam, that needed to be located outside
this titanium enclosure.
The JunoCam took some amazing pictures of Jupiter, like this one on the
left-hand side of Jupiter's south pole.
This image was actually of several images.
They're all put together to get it in all
daylight. But
after the first 34 orbits, JunoCam was operating
normally. Then you could see some radiation damage start to
appear.
At the 56th orbit, nearly all of JunoCam
image was actually corrupted.
And then we have these corrupted images. You get something like this.
So that image was taken November 22nd, 2023,
trying to capture a cyclone on Jupiter's north pole.
The engineers actually attempted to repair the
JunoCam by annealing, which a process of heating the device.
So, heating semiconductor material actually
allows this radiation-induced microscopic defects to actually
partially reorganize and so
recover. So the first attempt, they raised
JunoCam's heater to a temperature around 700 degrees Fahrenheit,
and afterwards they did see some improvement, but still being in the radiation
environment, you see the problem return.
So they made more and more attempts.
And after a while, the image quality actually began to dramatically
recover. And then were able to get a image like this.
Now, this is a image of Jupiter's moon, Io.
So after these annealing attempts, NASA actually reported that
the JunoCam
images were almost as good when it first launched.
So this image was of the north pole region of Jupiter's moon, Io,
during its 57th close passage of Jupiter.
It was taken on December 30th,
2023, so a little over a month that previous image was
taken. It wasn't a permanent fix. It's still in the radiation
environment.
In 2025, the image noise had returned during
Juno's extended mission.
But it definitely gave us this issue, definitely gives insight on how
to maintain spacecrafts in this highly
radiation environment.
So that's it for my presentation.
Here are all my references. I hope you learned something. Thank you.
All right.
Let's see where we were at. We were at
Fanita
Phel.
And she also provided a video, so let's take a look at that.
Can you all see it?
Yeah.
Great.
Good day, classmates. My name is Fanita Phel And my
presentation will be focused on the radiation environment's
impact to SpaceX's innovative pursuance
of an orbital AI data center. Four days
ago, The Economist asked whether SpaceX's
plan for a data center in space truly adds up.
I find the concept fascinating, because I find it brings
together two rapidly changing domains.
That is proliferated space architectures and artificial
intelligence.
Before I begin, these remarks reflect my own unclassified
academic analysis, and not an official position of the United States
Space Force, nor the Department of War.
As a Space Force field grade officer, I am naturally interested in the
innovation. However, I am equally interested in
mission assurance. An orbital computing capability is
only valuable if operators can trust its
output, especially when that output may eventually inform
time-critical decisions for the war fighter.
Therefore, I will narrow The Economist's broad feasibility question
to this week's course material.
Can a spacecraft packed with advanced
processors and memory remain
trustworthy after years in the radiation
belt?
And I cannot seem to put this on
slideshow, so we'll just do this page by page.
Before discussing radiation, I want to distinguish clearly
between an ambitious proposal and an operational capability.
The Economist reports that SpaceX's
AI1 reference design could operate at approximately
150 kilowatts of peak power, accommodate
72...
Before discussing radiation, I want to distinguish clearly-
Sorry, just started that back over
... proposal and an operational capability.
The Economist reports that SpaceX's
AI1 reference design could operate at approximately
150 kilowatts of peak power,
accommodate 72 advanced AI chips, and
remain in sunlight roughly 98% of the time.
In other words, this is closer to placing a
high-performance server rack in orbit than simply adding
another processor to a communication satellite.
The regulatory status also matters.
SpaceX requested authority for a system of up to one
million satellites operating between 500 and 2,000
kilometers in 30 degree and sun synchronous orbits.
The FCC accepted the application for filing and public comment.
That does not mean that the fleet has been authorized,
deployed, or radiation qualified.
I make that distinction not to diminish the innovation, but to
ensure that we evaluate it with the same disciplined engineering
rigor we would apply to any future operational system.
The proposed altitude range is especially important because there is
no single radiation value that represents this entire
constellation.
Near 500 kilometers, a satellite may still encounter trapped
protons while passing through the South Atlantic anomaly.
In a sun synchronous orbit, the spacecraft also reaches high magnetic
latitudes, where Earth provides less shielding from solar
energetic particles and galactic cosmic rays.
At the upper end of the filing, near 2,000 kilometers,
the spacecraft moves farther into the trapped particle environment
and generally requires a larger dose margin.
From a Space Force mission assurance perspective, this is a
fundamental requirements issue.
A node at 500 kilometers and 30 degrees inclination
should not inherit the same radiation assumptions or
qualification case as a node at 2,000 kilometers in a sun
synchronous orbit.
Orbit selection is therefore not only a power and communications
trade, it directly shapes reliability, shielding
mass, useful life, and operational risk.
Our course material separates radiation effects into cumulative
and prompt mechanisms. Total ionizing dose accumulates
over the mission and gradually changes semiconductor behavior.
Displacement damage disrupts the crystal lattice and is
particularly important for solar cells and optoelectronics.
Single-event effects can occur when one energetic
particle deposits enough charge to flip a bit,
create a transient trigger latch-up, or even cause destructive
burnout.
For an orbital AI system, the most concerning...
A resilient design would use d-
Uh-oh.
Looks like the video stopped.
Let me see what I can do about that.
Hmm.
All I get is black dots spinning in circles.
So I think we will have to leave that
one
for
a video. This PowerPoint slide, I think it's
just too big for my computer to handle.
I will post this online so that you can view it later.
Rachel, you're here tonight, right?
Yes, I am, ma'am.
My assessment is that radiation-
I think it just started back up again.
It's still going in circles, so let me do this.
You still want to show the video, or are you presenting live?
I prefer the video.
Okay.
If that's fine. Thank you.
Right on. Let me do that.
Hello, everyone. My name is Rachel Danover.
And let me share it.
And we will start it.
And for the current events presentation, I'm going to be presenting
on designing for the radiation environment.
So there are a few different effects of the radiation environment that can
happen on spacecraft. My presentation will primarily focus on the effects on
electronics. So there is the total ionizing
dose, which is the accumulated dose of radiation over time.
It's associated with lower energy particles, and it can
reduce the performance of a system by altering the doping of the silicon
inside the chips over time, as you can see in this top right image,
where we can see a particle affecting the doping.
And what this results in is slower turning on and off speeds,
and slower response times, as well as it can cause solar cell
degradation over time, meaning it won't produce as much
power as it would at the beginning of its life.
Then there are single event effects.
Probably the most well-known of them is the single event upsets,
which are bit flips caused by a single heavily ionized particle
passing through a transistor, which induces a charge large enough to
change the state of the node from a one to a zero,
or a zero to a one, depending.
Then there are single event transients, which are brief glitches in performance,
such as voltage spikes.
Then there are single event latch ups, which are parasitic loops
generating
a low impedance path in the transistor between power and ground.
And this can be fixed by power cycling.
Then there's single event burnout, which is the destruction of a device
due to high voltage that exceeds the breakdown voltage of the transistor, which
results in permanent failure.
Then there are single event gate ruptures,
which is the formation of a conducting path in the gate oxide, which you can
see demonstrated by this image here.
Then there are some mitigation approaches
to prevent these. One of the simplest ones would be to add
shielding.
This is very useful for stopping lower energy particles and is generally a
good method for reducing the total ionizing dose.
As you can see by this image here, there's another similar one in
the Tribble textbook that basically just highlights the
more
shield thickness that you have, the more radiation you're blocking.
However, at a certain point, it's not really
beneficial.
It's diminishing returns, essentially.
Then you would want to use rad-hard processors,
and there's a few different ways that processors can be considered
rad-hard. One is through oxide insulation.
So thin layers of oxide insulation are used to separate the active circuitry
from the bulk silicon substrate. Then there's triple modular
redundancy, or TMR, which uses three identical
circuits and uses majority rules if there's any discrepancies between the
circuits. So if you have one circuit that's malfunctioning due
to a single event effect, then the
other two most likely won't be, and so you can use those to
determine which
result is accurate.
Then there's just the general idea of using lower voltages, which can
reduce the risk of single event latch ups from occurring.
Then there's this technique called error detection by duplicated
instructions,
where you, for critical instructions, duplicate original
instructions with different registers and variables, and then once they're
executed, if there's a mismatch detected, then the error handling software is
invoked. Unlike the triple modular redundancy, where you can resolve the error
right there pretty much with just majority rules, the error
correction has to step in.
Then there are error correction codes, ECC,
which are basically codes
that are added to data to verify that there have been no changes.
So one example of this is EDAC, which is error detection and control, which
adds redundant bits to data, allowing the computer to detect if an error has
occurred by referencing the metadata provided by the redundant bits.
Then there is something called hardware scrubbing, where essentially,
during CPU downtime,
it runs a system that detects radiation-induced errors
and rewrites the data, if it's able to
Then finally,
just like how if you're having an issue with your computer and usually tech will
tell you, "Hey,
have you tried turning it on and off again?"
This works really well for clearing temporary errors
created by radiation,
because it clears the memory and then it forces the hardware to reinitialize,
helping to restore it back to a functioning state.
So when we look at design for
spacecraft to survive the radiation environment, generally
the approach that a lot of satellites
take is just to avoid it. But what if
your
probe is designed to go through the intense radiation belts and needs to stay
there
to study it? Then you're going to have to really
work hard to make sure that your design can survive that radiation.
And that's the case with the Van Allen probes.
So these probes were launched on the 30th of August,
2012, and they're two probes designed to study the
Van Allen radiation belts.
They had a highly elliptical orbit, so just like other strategies of just
kind of not entirely staying within the radiation belt
the entire time, it moved in and out of them.
It would move through the inner belt two times every nine hours, and then it would
be in the outer belt during apogee.
Its operations were expected to last for two years, but it lasted for six.
One of the probes is still
in orbit today.
And overall, it was designed to survive a total ionizing dose of 34
kilorads.
So what design decisions did the
creators make?
One important decision was that critical components could be power cycled
individually, in the event of a failure that required removal of
power. So instead of just having to power off or power cycle the
entire device,
you could just do an individual component, which could save
time. Then there was something called a command
loss timer, which was for both software and hardware,
that
would trigger an automatic power cycle if a specific
command was not received after so much time had passed.
Then additionally, EDAC and memory and hardware
scrubbing were used.
The power system itself used voltage
control and had a fault-tolerant voltage control shunt
regulator that could prevent voltage spikes from happening, so
preventing potential damaging voltages from occurring
within the system.
Then the solar panels themselves were coated in a
half millimeter of special coating that was designed to resist high-energy
radiation.
And then finally,
the simplest approach they took was just using thick
aluminum shielding,
as well as additional radiation shields in certain
sensitive environments.
And that would be the twin
Van Allen probes. I would recommend if you're
curious about other ways that you can design a spacecraft to survive the radiation
environment would be to check out the Europa Clipper mission, as
Europa is in a very radiated part
of
Jupiter's magnetosphere,
that the system had to be designed to be able to survive that for
multiple years. So there's definitely some interesting design
ideas there. But overall, here
are my references,
and I would like to thank you all very much for your time.
Okay. Thank you.
And then finally,
we have Emmanuel.
And I will share his screen.
Adeyomi.
Good day, everyone.
My name is Emmanuel Adeyomi.
The topic of my current event presentation is
radiation design
consideration.
Space radiation is made up of highly
energy particles that can affect spacecraft
during their missions.
Listed here are the main sources of space
radiation.
We have the solar energetic particles,
the galactic cosmic rays,
trapped electrons,
and trapped protons,
which are located in the Van
Allen belt.
And also listed here are the design concerns for
spacecraft.
Radiation affects spacecraft in different
ways.
Listed here I have-
Effects of radiation on spacecraft.
We have the total
ionizing dose,
which gradually weakens electronic components over
time,
while the displacement damage changes
the structure of semiconductor materials.
We have the single
event upset,
which can cause memory errors,
and the single event latch,
which may permanently
damage electronics.
It is also important to note that even
one energetic particle can sometimes
cause a major system failure, making
radiation protection very essential.
Radiation has become
an even bigger concern because Solar
Cycle
25 is nearing its peak,
leading to more frequent solar storm.
And
NASA's
Artemis mission and other commercial lunar
missions are also operating farther from the
Earth,
where radiation levels are very much
higher.
This has increased the need for better radiation forecasting
and improved spacecraft protection
technologies.
When
considering-
Radiation
... radiation design for spacecraft,
we should know that
engineers use several methods to protect
spacecraft from radiation.
These methods
or strategies include
radiation-hardening processors,
protective shielding,
error detection and correction systems,
redundant flight computers,
watchdog timers,
and
autonomous
fault recovery.
Together, all of these features improve reliability and
help spacecraft continue operating
even after a radiation
event.
For radiation shielding,
different shielding materials have different strengths.
For instance, aluminum is lightweight and commonly used,
but it can produce secondary
radiation.
And polyethylene provides better
protection against protons,
while composite materials reduce weight
but
are more expensive.
So engineers must carefully choose the right
material because adding more shielding does not
always improve protection.
Designing radiation protection always involves
trade-offs.
More shielding increases
spacecraft mass.
Better reliability usually increases
cost,
and stronger protection can reduce the
amount of payload the spacecraft
can carry.
So because of these challenges,
modern spacecraft
combine shielding,
hardened electronics, redundancy,
and smart software rather than
relying on just one solution.
So in summary, radiation is one of the biggest environmental
hazards in space.
It can damage electronics, shorten mission life,
and affect mission success.
Current missions like Artemis continue to
drive improvements in radiation protection,
and successful spacecraft depend on a combination of
shielding,
hardened electronics, and
fault-tolerant system design.
Here are the references I used for this presentation,
including NASA resources, ESA
publications,
ECSS standards, and textbooks on
spacecraft radiation effects.
Thank you all for listening.
Looking forward to your questions.
All right, great. We had four presentations
today. Well, three and a half.
I will post
Fanita's presentation on
Our Canvas website under this module.
So that's what we will do. Stop
share.
Let's go back to the slides.
And welcome to our last week of class.
This is the last lecture I plan on giving because next
week is dedicated for
finishing, well, me grading Milestone 2 for one,
but also finishing up the
touches on your final report, as well
as your final homeworks, as well as taking
the final exam. So I think that's plenty for you to
plan on doing. So
it was covered what is radiation in some of the previous
four presentations,
and
we'll define it as any energetic particle,
electrons, protons, heavier ions, gamma rays, X-rays.
And some of the effects that we'll talk about today will
be that it degrades bulk material properties.
It can displace or ionize material in its path.
It causes memory errors and,
Rachel went over some particular
effects on electronics. We'll go over that in more detail.
And then biological effects, which none of the speakers today talked
about. So we will definitely touch on this.
We did get to hear about
the main sources of radiation.
So those are...
Oops, started it back at the beginning.
Those are
the Van Allen
radiation belts, galactic cosmic rays, solar particle
events,
and the book only says that, but I would like to
add a fourth one on. Sometimes we do it to ourselves.
Sometimes we take RTGs along on
missions or
another type of power source such as nuclear power,
which could become more prominent in the future
since we're looking at going further
distances.
Radiation
categories are alpha particles,
for example,
beta particles, which are electrons or positrons, which, if you're
not familiar with positrons, those
are particles with the same charge
and mass as an electron, except it's positive.
Gamma rays are energetic photons emitting
from a nucleus
and, whoops, didn't mean to go there yet.
X-rays are radiation emitting from atomic electrons,
so they're not as powerful as beta or alpha
particles.
There are two main categories,
non-ionizing,
which damage material
and
tissues
by
the production
of
heat or atomic displacements.
And we'll talk a little bit about atomic displacement
shortly.
And ionizing are the most dangerous.
It has enough energy, or
I'll call it sufficient energy,
to remove
bound electrons from atoms
thus creating ions. You remove
electrons, you got ions.
And differences in charge
distributions.
A lot of electrons
missing from one part.
Whoops, I got those backwards. Distributions.
Releasing a lot of electrons from one part, then you have a highly
positive part of the charge distribution
compared to the neutral or negative.
But these are definitely the most responsible for
damage.
And I might say, especially in humans, and that's what we're going to start
off with
is
excuse me, some of the human effects.
We've already seen this before. The major
things that we have to worry about are solar particle
events, trapped radiation, Van Allen belts, galactic cosmic,
which are mostly hydrogen and helium
ions.
Yeah, positive ions and nuclear blasts in
space are things we carry
with us. So hopefully, the first three are
the persistent ones. Hopefully, we won't do anything stupid
and have a nuclear blast in space. That would
be a very devastating event.
Solar wind, we've seen this before.
And
it's a continuous stream of charged particles, mostly
electrons, protons, and
alpha particles. They typically travel about
300 to 800 kilometers per second and are
heated up.
And it is slowed and compressed
here at the bow shock.
About 13 to 15 of Earth radii,
it varies depending on the solar wind, from the Earth's center.
Then the solar wind is this, then
diverted around the magnetosphere and the
magnetopause here
is where dynamic pressure of the solar wind balances the
Earth's magnetic pressure. So that is an area where things
are kind of balanced, but they're very unstable.
So, in addition to auroras space weather and
astronaut
safety concerns,
the solar wind can also
create solar radiation
pressure, which we'll talk about in this lecture too.
Solar particle events, I think we've seen this
chart before. They coincide with
CMEs. Dominant constituent is
protons. Typically take three to five days to reach the
Earth. Geo, you can get exposed up
to 100 rads per year,
and that is very much above,
we'll talk about this later, the astronaut limit of 60
rems
per
lifetime.
And we will discuss how you relate rads,
R-A-Ds, to roentgen equivalent
man, which are rems. We'll discuss that shortly.
Sun sync, you can get up to 5,000 rads per year.
Category levels are shown here.
We typically only get a few extreme per year,
but strong and severe can still wreak havoc.
Van Allen radiation belts. Several of the speakers today talked about
that, so I will not belabor it.
But,
for example, at a spacecraft at 45-degree
inclination, the peaks would be about 3,000
kilometers, and those would consist of protons,
and that would still be considered LEO.
And at 25,000
kilometers,
that would be NEO, and that would be dominated by
electrons.
Greater than 45 degrees would get more
radiation because you don't really have the protection of the Van Allen
radiation belts. And it has
been the south, especially the Van Allen
radiation belts and the South Atlantic Anomaly,
have been associated with astronauts having
sleep interruptions due to flashes of
light that they see due to the radiation in those
belts or in the South Atlantic Anomaly.
So an extreme example of this is
Valentin Lebedev in
1982. He wrote a book about this. He
spent 211 days in space but
got severe depression about five months in, which would
be horrible to have.
But it was due to, they tracked it back to his
disrupted sleep cycle.
The radiation burst or the
radiation flashes that he got
was interrupting his circadian rhythms.
And also at that time, they didn't know that you weren't supposed to live with blue
light all the time,
so they had only blue light.
And he wrote a book about it. So if you're interested in finding
out more about that,
there is his diary.
Now, galactic cosmic rays were officially discovered in the
1800s, but we knew about as early
as 1780. And the reason is French
physicist Augustine
Coulomb,
which you probably know from coulomb charge from
electrical engineering,
was discovered because an electrically charged
sphere
that he was working on was suddenly not charged anymore.
And this was on Earth, and he's wondering, of course it was on Earth, and
he's wondering, "Hmm, why did that happen?" Well,
at that time, air was thought to be an insulator, not an electrical
conductor.
But Air can indeed conduct
electricity if molecules are charged
or ionized. So the atoms and
fragments of protons, electrons, atomic nuclei,
which travel at the speed of light,
probably was what defactor in his
loss
of,
electrical conductivity in his
sphere. Sources of
galactic cosmic rays are usually supernovas or the
end of a star's life, but it doesn't
always have to be. And this is a
demo from NASA's
Fermi Space Telescope, gamma ray
telescope, which is... Let me stop
sharing and share my new screen here.
Which is
a neat little app you can go to. You can
see what Fermi is currently predicting
all the time. And what we do know from
this, well, first off, Fermi gamma ray
telescope is in LEO.
What we do know is that there are two prominent
supernova remnants in the Milky Way, and where you see the
bright lights, that's one of them. They are along the ecliptic.
And then on the other side, there's the other one.
So I have provided the link here in case you want to
go to that
website there and check it out.
And back to my slides.
Okay, what else can happen?
Oh, I
forgot to say on the last slide, what are
galactic cosmic rays made of?
Mostly hydrogen protons,
90%. 90% would be
helium alpha particles or the nuclei, and then
1% would be other elements such as
heavy ions.
Now, what else can we do? We can do it to ourselves.
Heavy nuclear detonations in space.
Is that a real threat? Well,
have we done it to ourselves? In 1962,
the Starfish Prime program was developed in the United
States. You may not know about this.
And a 1.4-megaton nuclear bomb
was set off at 400, 900 kilometer.
Nope, 400-kilometer altitude. I can't read my own writing.
And that is part of Operation Fishbowl when
we were doing a lot of the nuclear test back then.
What it did is it generated a
electromagnetic pulse that damaged electrical systems in
Hawaii
900 miles away.
80% of the damage was in the form of X-rays,
20% in the form of neutrons or gamma rays.
It affected our Van Allen radiation belts for
about two months at a very high level,
and then lower and longer-term effects
lasted for 10 years.
In fact, the extra energetic
electrons from this nuclear detonation
formed their own higher radiation belts.
Six of our satellites failed completely, and
that is part of what led to our nuclear test ban
treaty in 1963.
The other thing that we can do to ourselves is take along
radioisotopic thermoelectric generators, or
RTGs. And why do we need those?
Well, if you take the Sun's irradiance at Mars,
you have about enough energy from solar
power to light a 40-watt light bulb.
So that's about 43% of Earth's
solar flux. And it gets worse as you go on
out. You might remember this from the beginning of the
semester or
term here.
It varies, or it reduces
dependent on
the radius from the Sun squared, where SC
is 1,367 watts per meter
squared, AU is the distance from the Sun to
the Earth, and R would be in
AUs.
So if you're going out past Mars, you really need to have some type of
nuclear power. I worked on the Cassini mission,
which went to Saturn and Saturn's moon, Titan,
and we had to use RTGs to provide enough power to get
out there. Now, I can tell you from personal experience,
that involved a lot of extra oversight
And safety concerns from both
the Department of Energy as well as the
Environmental Protection Agency.
We basically had to prove
and show through test demonstrations
that that RTG's case
would not be impacted by any amount of space debris
that could possibly be available
in our destination out to
Saturn.
And it was a huge political issue. In fact, on the day
of launch, we had a lot of protesters there
that said, basically, we're going to kill everyone on the Earth because
this RTG was going to explode. And like some
of the
protesters said, it was going to kill
everyone. Also,
we were flying by, we were doing a
Venus-Earth-Jupiter flybys, and they were concerned that
when it flew back by the Earth, we would crash into the Earth
and kill everyone. Well, neither of those happened, and we ended up
going out to Saturn and working just fine.
But if we had had humans on this flight, that would have
been a different story because they then would have got
radiation from the RTGs.
So,
power generation, it's basically through the radioactive decay of
nuclear isotopes. Plutonium is what we used
on the Cassini mission. Now, what are the effects
on the human body, radiobiology?
We went through the NASA Human Research Roadmap
and evaluated it for a mission on Ceres.
But one of the main ones, look here
for
Mars,
is even a longer
term orbital surface
is considered very high risk. So if you remember the
first
number is the risk of it, and the second
number are the consequences.
NASA's evaluation right now says that for
long-duration orbital surface
missions, we have a high probability of having a radiation
damage, and we need to characterize that and do something
about it. For Mars, it's even worse.
Both of those even less than one year are three by
threes.
The main ones are risk of acute and late
central
nervous system effects.
And that means that once you get there and exposed to the
radiation, you could either have immediate effects to your nervous
system, or you could have some when they get back.
Acute radiation syndromes due to solar particle events,
cardiovascular diseases, and degenerative
tissue, as well as the risk of cancer.
So even if you are going to go on a Mars mission,
you may as well stay there, because if you come back,
you're probably going to have some of these issues that
arrive.
So in other words, you won't die on the mission, probably, but you will die
soon afterwards.
All are affected by the mission duration trajectory.
And that is another reason we're not
considering sending humans to Mercury or Venus, even
for gravity assist, because that
would require them to be inundated by an
excessive amount of radiation. Some things that you can do
for that is shielding, which was
mentioned in one of the presentations earlier in this lecture,
and then use ultra-high molecular weight
polyethylene or different polymers.
UCCS just, in fact,
have flown our second high-altitude balloon experiment.
We just got it back last week with a
20-hour flight on a platform that
will
fly out of Fort
Sumner, New Mexico in mid-August.
And what we're doing is we're looking at shielding
a Geiger counter and some electronics with the
UHMWPE
specific polymer and then having an
unprotected Geiger counter and
electronics and compare the two.
Twenty hours isn't a long time, but we expect we will be able
to get some differences between the two.
So I'm looking forward to seeing the results of that flight
experiment.
Radiation definitions. Radiobiology.
What is radiobiology? It's pretty
straightforward in that it's biology that
specializes in the study of the effects of
radiation on biological
molecules.
Cell tissues, whole organisms, whatever the case
may be. So it's the effect of radiation on living
things. And we're particularly
interested in understanding the molecular
changes responsible for the radiation effects,
the cancer, the genetic changes,
cell impairment, or even death.
Scott Kelly, if you've ever read his book, "Endurance,"
which I would highly recommend, talks about
the effects of the flashes that he got from radiation.
But if you go on to follow his recent
developments, they determined that some of his DNA
had permanently been
altered because of his radiation exposure
for that long duration of time he had been up
there. Not all kinds of radiation is harmful.
Radiation includes all effects of
highly energetic particles, but
radio waves, microwaves, and infrared just
basically transfer heat, so they're not a big
deal.
The other
separation we have is deterministic and
stochastic. So deterministic is what we'll
focus on. That is the loss of
tissue
due to
cell degradation.
And then stochastic, I'm mentioning this because it's mentioned
in Tribble,
stochastic is the probability of occurrence.
So we're not going to focus a whole lot on that.
We're going to focus on mostly,
let's see if I could spell occurrence correctly,
deterministic. What are the human effects?
And NASA goes by
the principle of ALARA,
as low as reasonably possible.
We can't eliminate
all of the radiation effects,
but we can make them as low as realistically possible.
So minimize radiation exposure and
establish an upper bound, and that
is 60
rems per lifetime.
And I'll talk more about that in a moment.
Activity is the rate at which a source
decays
or the number of atoms that decay and emit radiation per
unit time.
Other things you may hear related to activity are
becquerel,
B-E-C-Q-U-E-R-E,
which is an SI unit which describes the
quantity of the radioactive material in
which the atom decays. We're not going to use that a whole lot
in this class other than mentioning it here.
And something you may have heard of is the curie,
which is a C-I, which is a quantity of
radioactive material in which
3.7 times 10 to the 10 atoms decay per
second. So that's basically the amount of
radiation emitted by one gram of radian
in
226 per second. We're not going to use that a whole lot.
We are going to use the next couple ones.
Exposure is the measurement of the ionization produced
by X-rays and gamma rays in dry air,
and roentgen is the amount of
charge
introduced
in dry air.
One roentgen produces a small
amount, 2.58 times 10 to the minus 4 coulombs
per kilogram,
but that can increase significantly if
it's in soft tissue
for humans.
The rad is called the radiation
absorbed dose, and we've already talked about
that.
And it's the amount of
radiation that would deposit 0.01
joules per kilogram of the material,
and that is an SI measure. Gray
is equal to 100 rads.
Specific absorption rate
For humans
is the rate at which energy is absorbed
per unit mass. So that would be a watts per
kilogram measurement.
So we're getting to the important thing right here.
The absorbed dose is the amount of any type of
radiation energy deposited in a unit mass of
energy material, and that is measured in
Grays, which we already introduced.
Equivalent dose is the normalized damage,
and we use a much smaller measurement called a
Sievert for that, and that is another
measure of biological damage.
You're probably wondering right now, okay, I
got 20 different definitions. Which ones are the important ones?
Here they are. Radiation
for humans, anyway.
Biological effectiveness
typically given
in Sieverts or R...
Let me finish writing this.
Effectiveness
in Sieverts,
and that Sievert accounts for how
damaging that radiation is to the human body.
So I'll give some examples in just a minute, but
RBEs can range from, on Earth we're
protected, so the RBE would be
one, whereas if we're in the Van Allen radiation belts, it would be
higher than that because you're exposed to
higher radiation. That would be a factor
of five to seven.
So what we're interested in, we've already introduced the
rad, we're interested in the
roentgen equivalent man, where
REM is RAD times
RBE, and most of the references
that you'll find will report things in rads,
especially in free space travel
between the Earth and other planets.
So here is a chart
explaining what
the various RBEs for. So if you're on Earth, it's
one. If you're in the radiation belt, five to seven.
If you're in a region of high-charge particles, you're getting
bombarded by galactic rays or whatever, that
would be an RBE of 10, and I provided the damage
thresholds right here on the right side in
Grays so that you can get an idea of
how much humans and animals,
biological things are vulnerable.
Very low damage thresholds compared
to most of the electronics and structural
metals that we fly.
So remember, one Sievert
is 100 rem,
and that would be
well above
the limit on any of these damage thresholds for
humans to survive.
So you might wonder, what is the dose limit for
humans? NASA used to evaluate
those based on gender and age,
and up until I think it was
2022,
they used to break it out by gender, age.
So in fact, young women had the
lower radiation exposure limit,
whereas old men had the highest radiation
exposure limit,
mainly based on
reproductive organs. But in
2022, NASA decided to limit
the life
accumulation of 60 rems or
600 millisieverts.
And some of the things that can happen for acute
exposure, this would be short-term.
You can get fast-reproducing cells that can
contribute to cancer.
You can get gastrointestinal issues,
bone marrow loss,
and exercise really doesn't help that.
It helps it a little bit, but not a whole lot.
Fatigue
and loss of appetite,
short-term.
Long-term, you can get cataracts, which you
probably you wouldn't
find out until you got back to Earth on one of these
missions. DNA altered, we already talked about that with
Scott Kelly.
Hemorrhaging.
I'm not entirely sure how to spell this.
That does not look right, but it might be. I don't know.
And your hair falls out.
So typical exposure levels. Sea
level, we get about 0.1 per year. Colorado
Springs, we get double that.
Some of the things, Skylab, we didn't know much about
radiation protection back then. So 78
rems per year would be well over the limit now.
Shuttle.
Fortunately, shuttle flights didn't last that long, so that's pretty
minimal. But on the ISS, we
have provided enough radiation protection
to get it down to about 18 rems per year.
And then on the right-hand side are the effects
up to mortality. And if you
get 1,000 rems, you're not going to survive.
Okay, so what does that mean? That means
that you're going to have a homework problem on this,
and this is it.
We're going to Mars. We're going to send humans to Mars,
and we need to pass through several hostile
environments. The Van Allen radiation belts, which we're
going to get around as much as possible
by following
a
northern high inclination launch, or high...
I guess that would be called
azimuth launch.
We will skirt along the Van Allen radiation belts,
but we'll still be affected by it by a little.
So that's going to be our first
hostile environment to get through.
And don't forget, if you send a mission to Mars, you also need to
send them back. So you're going to be sending them back through that same
environment. So whatever you get for outgoing, you
should double that because you'll be coming back in that way.
These are the radiation dosages in table
one. For each of those, I have given you
a spacecraft speed of just an
average of 25,000 kilometers per hour
along the indicated path, and I got that path from the
Apollo 11 mission.
You will also need to find a reference that provides trajectory
information for missions in the 2025 to
2050 timeframe. I wrote a book when
I worked at NASA
that was
human trajectories
to Mars in the years 2014 through
2024. That's obviously outdated now.
I did provide an updated reference, and you
can use that to find trajectory information.
How long are you going to take to get to Mars?
How long are you going to stay on Mars?
How long are you going to need to come back from Mars?
For the transient radiation model,
you are assuming
either no shield thickness. That's going to be what you
write about. So you will pick these values on the left-hand
side.
Basically, no radiation protection, or
aluminum shielding. I think this is aluminum. Yeah, I think it's aluminum.
So,
solar cosmic radiation means
of 50% and 99%, 50% is the average.
I would use the 99%. That means only 1% of events
would be outside of that. So you will tally up the
galactic cosmic rays and the solar cosmic radiation
or,
yeah, the solar radiation of
99% and total those up. And
remember, those are in rads. So you'll have to
decide in free space what the radiation
biological effectiveness is. But those can
be pretty high pretty quickly.
The landing site will be Jezero Crater.
I've shown you one representative timeline on the
right-hand side here,
and
I have even provided a representative
trajectory which you can determine how long it's going to take to
get there, how long it stays on Mars.
But feel free to look up your own. Cosmic
radiation environment on Mars. You will multiply this
times
the number of years that you're spending on Mars.
I recommend landing at the Jezero Crater, where
you have the lowest radiation dose, which makes sense.
Don't land in a red region, because that's going to be your worst case.
So
that you will determine if with no shielding,
a human mission to Mars would be feasible.
I'll tell you right now, the answer is no, it won't be.
So part C will be, what can you help to mitigate
radiation concerns? And one chart you have is this
one, where you have the shield thickness
versus the absorbed dose, and you can help a
lot.
The absorbed dose can help a lot. Notice it doesn't help much with
galactic cosmic rays, though.
Not a whole lot helps against
GCRs because they're so energetic.
Okay, and that was it for part one.
Part two. Now that we know something about
the radiation environment and its effect on humans,
let's talk a little more about its effect on
spacecraft components.
So let me share this again.
Here we go.
And fortunately, several of our presenters today
covered this material, so I won't go into it in a lot of
detail because I also want to allow time for
a review and what's going to be on the final, as
well as expectations for the final report.
So,
now that we know what radiation does to humans, which
is usually bad, what does it do to spacecraft?
And that is typically in the form of single event
phenomena, which has a lot of different
components to it. We will also look at solar radiation
pressure. If you have taken an ADACS course
in this
program or a space systems engineering course, that
might be redundant, but I thought it was important for those
who might not be exposed to this concept.
Single event phenomena are circuit changes,
upsets, or damage caused by one or a small
number of energetic photons or particles.
Some electrical components are less susceptible.
So if you take the basic ones like a resistor, it's not going to be affected.
Capacitors, inductors, relatively immune,
but the active components, transistors, diodes,
bipolar transistors,
integrated circuits, semiconductors, are all going
to be affected.
Solar radiation pressure, however, is a
cyclic torque on an Earth
vehicle. Or if you're
outside of the Sun, it's cyclic
because you go into the eclipse occasionally, so it only happens on
the Sun side. But if you're out on a mission from Earth
to Mars, you're going to be exposed to it the whole time.
It depends strongly on the surface, as well
as
the surface type of surface,
but also the area that's facing the Sun.
Like drag, drag is mostly a concern
in
LEO, however, solar radiation pressure
is probably the biggest concern in GEO.
What can happen to electrical components?
I think I saw this earlier in one of the student presentations,
but what can happen is an energizing
particle can come through, and if it's ionized, it can
create this breakup of positive and negative
ions, and
that can wreak havoc on your
electronics. So for example,
this is divided into four main areas.
It's debatable depending on which textbook you use, but
Pizzicanna uses four main areas. A
single-event upset is what we call a
soft error. It can be recovered from.
So that pair of
electrons going through the material
or ions going through the material, it creates a
transient pulse in an analog device or a
circuit, or it can provide a bit flip in the
terms in a digital logic
circuit.
But
it can often be recovered through software
that checks for those type of upsets
or just a reset of the
electronic device that you're working with.
Burnout, on the other hand, that is called SEB,
results in excessive power draw in a power
transistor, mostly caused by that
ionization trail, and that can cause permanent
destructive failure.
Basically, it produces this conducting
channel between the two layers
separated by a depletion region.
Single event latch up, this was also covered before.
We call that SEL.
Caused by excessive power draw, but this time it causes a short
circuit
in the supply and ground semiconductors and can
result in very large currents.
It can often be recovered through a shutdown
or restart, but you want to make sure you're
limiting your power current or voltage to make sure
you don't get these spikes.
That can especially cause heating, which can burn out, especially at large
charges, which can burn out components.
And then we have,
let's see.
I didn't write this on here, but someone mentioned it earlier,
single event hard errors.
Which is a permanent change. For example, a stuck bit
stays in that one or zero state in a logic device.
Overall,
these upsets have gotten more prominent as devices get
smaller and smaller, like we see here on Earth, and
have more diodes and transistors and other
active electrical components.
I think this was covered really, really well in one of the
presentations today,
so I'm not going to go over it a whole lot.
But
you can have error detection and correction codes which identify
and correct corrupted memory bits.
Oops, not quite there yet. Watchdog timers that will
automatically reset processors that
become non-responsive over a period of time.
Redundancy is always a great idea.
And then I know this was mentioned, majority voting.
So you would have maybe three or multiple
systems keeping track of the same
function that you want it to do. If one goes out,
you would isolate that, reboot the malfunctioning unit,
and go with whatever the other two or more systems say to
do.
This is...
Oops, I forgot to put a label on here.
This is single event upsets on a
mission called
UOSAT 2,
which was pretty much in a circular orbit.
It was 679 by 697
in LEO,
so in LEO. And you can see the great number
of South Atlantic anomaly upsets.
Those are mostly due to protons, but if you look up in the polar
regions, you can also see a lot up here,
how they are
prominent in those regions, and those ones are mostly due
to galactic cosmic rays. So
these are due to Van Allen radiation
belts, solar event
phenomena,
and South Atlantic anomaly. The ones up in the
polar regions, we just don't have a magnetic field up there
that protects us as much, are due to galactic
cosmic rays.
Other times, we have single event transients,
temperature, voltage, or current pulse.
So these can change a stored bit,
but it is a momentary glitch, so those can be
recovered from. Single event functional interrupt disrupts
the internal control logic, and the device enters
into an abnormal operating state
from which it can't recover without external intervention.
So those are dangerous. The most
destructive one is single event gate rupture.
That is a catastrophic permanent failure,
especially for MOS
semiconductors, or metal oxide semiconductors,
and that creates a conductive path through
the gate oxide which causes the transistor
to fail permanently. So that is not good.
So this table summarizes all of those effects depending
on what the component is,
and it splits them up as potentially not destructive
and potentially destructive. Notice
the single event gate and
single event gate rupture and
SEBs can
affect power metal oxide semiconductors a
lot and create that catastrophic failures,
but so can single event latch
ups
and SEHE.
Single event upsets, these are all potentially non-destructive.
You get these, you just reset or reboot,
isolate, or carry on.
Digital ICs, electric...
Let's see.
Yeah, digital ICs
are particularly vulnerable to transient
effects
and,
let's see, ADC and DAC,
analog-to-digital converters, digital-to-analog
converters are susceptible to both, whereas
optoelectronics, charge couple devices, or CMOS
are
susceptible to
CCDs, nondestructive,
CMOS, both categories. So the bottom line
is not all
effects are equally severe in this
Okay.
So that is how things affect
inside the spacecraft. So we covered this.
Now we're going to talk about some things I asked you to do
in the design project, gravity gradient torque, solar radiation
pressure, aerodynamic drag, and magnetic torque,
and we are going to concentrate on solar radiation pressure
today.
These are the equations that I'd like you to use for those.
This is from SMAD, Space Mission Analysis and
Design by Larson and some other
authors. These are what I want you to concentrate on.
What we're going to do today is an example for solar radiation
pressure.
So,
here they are.
F is the solar constant, 1367. We've been
using that. C is the speed of light.
C is the location of the center of solar pressure.
I'm not going to ask you to calculate that for this example
or your homework.
You may need to for your design project if your design
is not symmetric. CG is the center of gravity.
We will calculate that.
Q, we'll use 0.6, and I will use
zero degrees because that is the incident from
the sun that it is hitting you,
and most of the time, we will be using sun-tracking solar
arrays. So, whoops, I shouldn't have marked that I.
Usually called theta. We'll use I is equal to zero,
making this term go to one.
Then you will design your reaction wheels taking that
torque
and adding on a 25% margin factor.
And this is the moment.
And the
references I'm using kind of transfer back between
moment and torque.
So I'm going to call it moment or torque because they mean the
same thing in what we're doing here, at least,
and that will help you size your reaction wheels.
That means if your torque is less than 0.05
newton-meters, you would have 5 kilograms per
wheel times 10 watts per each wheel
power,
mid-size and large sats. One thing to
note here is typically, reaction
and momentum wheels will involve four wheels.
So if you're going to account for mass, you would account
for mass times four wheels.
Same for the power.
And that is a summary of
what happens in the radiation environment.
So what I wanted to do next is spend a few minutes talking about
homework problem six. This is an
asymmetric Starlink satellite,
which have been flown or are still currently flying.
We have a spacecraft body with a size mass of 30
kilograms, solar array given size and a mass
of 197 kilograms. They are sun tracking,
so that incident angle would indeed be equal
to zero, and you may assume it's in an orbit
so that it is facing the sun at all times.
I'd like you to find the solar radiation pressure
force on the satellite and then recommend what
size and power needs you would get.
So
just to get you started on this, I'm not going to go into a lot of detail
because y'all are graduate students, and, whoops,
I'm not a good artist.
And these are my solar arrays going up.
So our dimensions are
10.9 meters.
This is sun-facing. These are the solar arrays.
This would be the dimension of 1.6 meters.
This would be 1.2 meters. This is not drawn to scale,
and this dimension would be 3.2 meters.
Just to get us all on the same page.
Mass of
satellite is 30 kilograms, relatively small.
The mass of the solar arrays is 197
kilograms. Pretty high.
You're given the center pressure is 6.03 meters,
so we want to find the force
is Fs As,
one plus q
cosine of the incidence angle divided by
C.
And then
moment is F
times C
Center of pressure minus CG, I think,
was that an absolute value? I think it was.
No, it doesn't matter.
You're mostly interested in the magnitude anyway.
So how would you calculate the
area? Well, what I would suggest you do is take the
entire frontal area, so that would be the things
I've mentioned with hash marks there.
As then would be 10.9
times 3.2 sun facing,
plus
3.2 times 1.2.
So that would give you that.
And you can figure out from that the force.
Now,
I used to have students calculate the center pressure, but
I found out that most of you forgot fluids by now,
and that's why I gave you the center pressure, because I was getting all
sorts of different answers. But what I do expect you to
do is to calculate the center of gravity.
And you might recall the center of gravity is the
sum of the masses times the distance
to the CGs,
divided by the mass total.
I established the mass to be zero at
the bottom of Starlink. It's actually pointed at the
page. My graphic doesn't do it justice
there. And if you look at the center
of mass of the
Starlink body itself, that would
be at 0.6 meters
times the 30 that
it
has the mass of,
times, let's see. I'll go to the next line.
Plus,
we would have
1.2
plus 10.9 divided by
2 times 197,
all divided by 227,
which is the sum of 197 plus 30. And that will
give your CG, which you can use in this
equation.
So that is why I'm looking there.
Notice this is only one disturbance out of three,
and we also are not including in this class any
effects due to slewing or moving the
satellite from location or from one
angle to another. So if you get a small answer,
that's what I expect you to get here.
And
you will still have to calculate the other effects.
I think they're pretty straightforward
for those on your homework problem.
Don't forget,
when you're calculating the total, to add in that
25% margin factor to size your
momentum or reaction wells.
Okay, and that was part two.
Let's move on to part three,
which will give you another
help with your homework problem. That last
section was probably way more than I should have helped you, but I
find that if I don't give some guidance on this problem,
I get a slew of different answers. So
that's why I gave you a little more direction there.
Okay.
So this section is pretty...
Whoops. Let me find my slides here, my notes.
There we go.
It's not an introduction to radiation really, but it kind of is
because
we're going to go over some of the details about how some of these
displacements and impacts to the
hardware and electronics mean.
So an example,
you've probably seen umpteen zillion examples of the EE
mag spectrum, but this is one that
shows it in terms of energy,
which is a little different. And notice that the higher energy,
unlike what we usually see when we're looking at it via
wavelengths, is the higher energy is on the left.
Now in this, the higher energy is on the right.
So these are some of the effects. So
typical energy
ranges.
And we're using the governing equation, energy is
equal to Planck's constant times the frequency.
Planck's constant is equal to... Whoops
4.135668
times 10 to the minus
eVs per hertz. So that would be, I guess, EV...
Yeah, frequency is in hertz, so yeah, that would work
out. Typical energy ranges. So for
a solar photon,
we would have a typical energy range in
electron volts of 0.1 through
0.6. Not a whole lot.
Solar wind, a little more powerful.
10 to the 3rd through 10 to the 4th.
Trapped,
in other words, Van Allen radiation belts
or South Atlantic Anomaly included in that.
4 times 10 to the 4th through 4 times 10 to
the 5th.
As I go up here, the energy ranges will get higher.
Solar particle events,
more dangerous at
2 times 10 to the 4th
through 2 times 10 to the
8th.
Cosmic rays
are the most energetic. That is an important thing to note.
Solar rays are
energetic, but when the solar
cycle goes down, cosmic rays increase
and vice versa. So
solar particle events increase,
cosmic rays decrease and vice versa.
So you're actually more vulnerable to cosmic rays
when the solar cycle is at a min.
But these can be 10 to the 6th times through 10 to the 12th,
which is high energy.
So we're going to do an example. A particular event
produced radiation with an energy of 100 kilo
electron volts. First off, what is its frequency?
So we know E is equal to 100 kilo
electron volts.
So using E, what was the equation
before, is equal to hf.
F is equal to E divided by h.
Whoops, little h.
Is equal to
100,000 electron
volts
divided by
4.135668
times 10 to the minus
15 eVs per hertz. It's not in kilo
electron volts, so you have to make sure to do that
conversion, and that would be
2.42 times 10 to the
19th
hertz.
What is its wavelength? Well, that's pretty straightforward to
do. Oh, by the way, that's very high.
That's a very high frequency. That's greater than
terahertz.
Which is 10 to the 12th, so that's a very,
very high frequency. Lot of energy.
The wavelength should be very small.
We know that's equal to C divided by F,
or 3 times 10 to the 8th meters
per second
divided by
2.42 times 10 to the 19
hertz.
So we're left with meters. We're left with
1.24 times 10 to the minus
11 meters.
Or
12.4
picometers.
The likely source,
if we go back to our chart here,
we were at
10 to the minus 11, 10 to the minus 11
is here.
We would probably be in the upper X-ray
or lower gamma ray range, so
high
energy
X-rays
or low
energy gamma rays.
Yep.
Okay. So that was an example.
Second example, I guess.
So correlation of charged particle flux density with solar
activity.
This is important. You might want to note this down.
Let's just kind of summarize. If we have the solar
wind
During solar min
and during solar max,
we will look at these effects.
Solar min,
low.
Of course, solar wind would be low during solar min.
Solar wind would be high during solar max.
Trapped radiation.
We're going to split this up.
Didn't have an answer here. Into
electrons
and protons.
Electrons,
low during solar min.
High during, whoops, what happened to my screen?
High during solar max. A lot more energetic particles
can come along and break those electrons
away. Solar min, you got more galactic cosmic
rays, which
are
characterized by protons, so these would
be the opposite. And then galactic cosmic
rays
would
obviously be high during solar min
and low during solar max.
And then if we look at solar particle events, of course, those would
be high during solar max and
low during solar min.
So that was kind of a summary of everything that we've talked about
so far, except for the human effects.
So how do radioactive substances occur?
Well, basically, they have excess nucleus energy, excess
neutrons or protons, and are very
unstable.
So to achieve stability,
radiation is emitted, and we have several
categories. Alpha particles consist of two
protons, two neutrons,
and can be stopped by a thin piece of paper.
So they're not that dangerous.
Beta particles are electrons or
positrons, which are the same as an
electron, mass and charge, except for posit--
I spelt that wrong, except for positive.
Yeah.
Can be stopped by clothing
or one inch of plastic, and it
doesn't really have to be a special plastic at all.
Not any special type of polymer.
Gamma rays is the reduced energy state of
the nucleus, and that can be stopped by
inches,
two feet
of concrete.
Or you might wonder what that would be in lead.
That would be one inch of lead, but both
of those are very heavy, so those are not the best
solutions for space systems.
Some interaction mechanisms. We have the photoelectric
effect.
There are three primary methods or
interactions of photons with matter.
This is the first of three. The photoelectric effect is
the interaction of an incident photon in which all of its
energy is transferred into a bound
electron, which ejects the electron
from the atom.
So if an inner electron is
ejected, an electron from a higher shell will fill
the vacancy, and that emits a photon,
typically an X-ray. So the principal method of
energy transfer with photon energies less than
50 kilo electron volts is the photoelectron
effect. So these can result in alpha
and beta particles.
Compton scattering is the next. That is the interaction of an
incident photon in which it loses enough energy to
an orbit or free electron to cause
ejection of the electron. So the remaining
photon energy is emitted as a newer, lower
energy photon.
The principal method of energy transfer
between 50 kilo electron volts, I'll
summarize this in a minute, and five mega electron volts,
and this is usually gamma radiation.
So getting worse
in effects on electronics in the human body.
And then we have pair production, where it
creates a particle and its antiparticle.
So an incident photon with the nucleus
can present that electron positron pair,
and it
Positrons, by the way, have a very short timeline,
but basically, this process annihilates
the electrons and produces two gamma rays and produces
energy much higher than the previous two effects.
So this is a summary of those
photoelectron. Electric dominates
in the lower energy, Compton dominates in the
middle, and pair production dominates in the higher
energies.
Now we're going to look at some attenuation
calculations, and what we're looking
at is
several terms here, the scattering cross-section, which I
have defined here, but we're interested in the photon flux
density. So that's what we're ultimately interested
in. And to explain it in words, the scattering
cross-section
governs the probability of the interaction of radiation
with an atom, and that consists of all three
effects: photoelectric,
Compton,
pair production.
So we have this equation here,
and dI is the change in flux
density in photons per centimeter squared
second, and N is the number density of the
target, and dx is your target thickness.
So we'll do an example here in just a minute.
To find the
photon flux density change,
you can use this equation where we
find that dI is sigma natural
log of
the target thickness in centimeters
and
mu,
let's
define it from here, is called the linear
attenuation coefficient.
And one per centimeter squared.
It's often given as the half-value life
or half-value layer.
Let me define that. Half-value
layer,
which is typically in centimeters, and that is the distance a
photon beam travels in an absorbing
medium in which it loses half of its
flux density.
So we'll do an example. Determine the fraction remaining of the
flux density of a one mega electron volt gamma
ray that travels one in 10 centimeters in lead,
assuming the half-value layer is
0.85 centimeters. So how do we start
this? Well, we start with our known.
HVL is
natural log of two
divided by mu.
So mu
is natural log of two
divided by the half-value layer,
and
LN
two divided by 0.85
is
0.81547
one per
centimeter.
So I is I naught, my
starting photon flux density, E to the minus
mu X,
or the fraction that's lost is I
divided by I naught, is E
to the minus
0.81547
times one centimeter,
is equal to
0.442 or
44.2%.
So that is a measure of how much energy is left.
So through
one
centimeter in lead,
you get a reduction of
44.2%.
And then if you repeat for 10 centimeters
is equal to
2.874
times 10 to the minus 4 or
0.0287%. So you
see that,
as expected, 10 centimeters of
lead reduces the
energy
to 0.0287% of its original.
So your homework problem, this is problem three,
is to basically do the same thing
except you're looking at lucite.
Okay.
So,
maybe it wasn't this class, maybe it was my undergraduate class,
I don't remember exactly who said this, but several
of you mentioned displacement damage or
bulk damage. This is how it works.
The primary particle coming in
can make one of those
particles or atoms deflect,
and it will leave vacancies or
push atoms into places they
don't belong.
So,
in other words, it upsets how
symmetric the lattice and material
stays.
And that can be interstitial,
where you just have those atoms in the wrong
places, or it can be in the form of a vacancy.
So why is this important? Electronic devices rely on
diffusion of charge carriers through semiconductor
materials, so this is especially
a concern
with semiconductor materials.
So radiation environment and its effects.
I intended, but I didn't get through this in my
graduation class, to talk about some parameters
involving
linear energy transfer and stopping power,
but I didn't have time to do that in my undergraduate class this semester.
So I took out two homework problems on that
for you all also, so we can stay consistent
for
homework.
Okay.
I will stop for questions at the end.
Let's see. We are going to go to a quick review, a quick
couple of review slides,
and then I'm going to talk about what's going to be on the exam
and the final project.
Okay. Review part one. All right. So
I also wanted to introduce you to a couple of
resources that I find informative.
Maybe you're already exposed to this, maybe not, but I subscribe to a
lot of these and stay current or try to stay
current at least. Who can stay current in this environment?
But I try to stay current in what's going on in
aerospace, and this is how. So first I'm going to
review the course objectives, space resources,
course review, final logistics, and final project.
These are the course objectives. We did not cover a lot of
space weather, although we did in a way because
we talked about the interaction of the space of the
sun with the Earth. So that's what I meant by
space weather.
And then the rest of this we covered:
space environmental hazards, space environment on spacecraft.
We covered
six main areas. We covered vacuum,
plasma, radiation,
neutral,
MMOD, and bioastronautics.
Space resources. Of course, I
posted as much as I could
chapters from Tribble,
which is more an undergraduate version of the space environment.
Pisacane is more of a graduate reference, so if you really
want to delve into this stuff or want a good reference, I would recommend
this one.
Some additional resources. National Academies Press,
if you haven't heard of them, they produce
most of the latest to greatest.
And this is a government agency, I believe,
on what's going on in NASA and the rest of
the DoD regarding
space studies. And it doesn't just concentrate
on Earth space studies either. It concentrates
on other spacecraft or human
missions going to other parts of our solar system.
NASA Tech Briefs, this is one I definitely recommend you
subscribe to. This will give you the latest and greatest in NASA,
and these are all links that I provided here.
And the NASA webinars. They have webinars that are free for
you to attend that provide information on different areas
you can delve into more deeply.
Spaceflight Now, that's my go-to.
That's
been my go-to for a lot of years on what is the
latest and greatest going on. If there's a SpaceX
launch, they'll feature that. If there's a military
launch, they'll feature that. It's just great to keep up with
the latest and greatest in the space industry.
Space Scoop, Lockheed Martin. Now, it will be a little biased
towards their programs. Not biased, but a little
more focused on their programs like DaVinci and Veritas,
which are going back to Venus here pretty soon.
But a word of warning, if you sign up for Space
Scoop, they'll send you everything.
They will also send you advances in aeronautics
and electronics. So it's kind of cool,
but it may be a little bit more than what you want to look
at, but you can always delete it if you don't want it.
NASA Explorer Newsletter is another good one that
provides updated information on what NASA's up to.
European Space Agency, they do a lot of stuff,
and we don't necessarily have insight into that as
a typical American. So that's why I like to
subscribe to this to find out what ESA
is doing. Space Foundation News is right here
in
the Colorado Springs, and this is, of
course, where we have the big space symposium every year, and they will
give you the latest updates on their end.
Okay. So what did we cover? We covered chapters
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 in Tribble, as well as some
additional bioastronautics readings.
We started with where is space? Where does it
start?
We learned that in LEO, we have a lot of effects,
mostly including drag. Everyone in
both LEO and GEO and MEO have to worry about the vacuum
environment. LEO is more predominantly worried
about
orbital debris, whereas GEO is more worried about
micrometeoroids. Plasma
can affect everyone, but probably not a whole
lot in GEO. However, it can
cause some extreme temperature variations in GEO, so you have
to look out for that, too.
Not as much effects in LEO. So again, plasma,
you can have some large
potential voltage differences in GEO
satellites.
Radiation, we discuss mostly
in GEO. You have to worry
about solar radiation pressure. In all the orbits,
you have to worry about
radiation.
In bioastronautics, we're only in LEO right now.
Although we've gone around the Moon, most of the
effects we've studied have been in LEO.
Why do we worry about the space environment?
Well, we discovered on day one that about one-fourth
of all spacecraft anomalies are related to the space
environment, and you're well aware of that, especially with the
research you did throughout the semester.
What object most strongly affects the space environment?
Obviously, not the Earth here, or
maybe that's the Moon. I don't know.
Anyway, it's the Sun, and we know that
solar events,
solar max and solar min can greatly affect what's going on, but
we're really not protected either way because once solar max goes
up, galactic cosmic rays go down and vice versa.
So low solar events, high galactic cosmic rays, and
those are the most energetic.
Two primary forms of energy output were EMAG
radiation and charged particles. This is actually a chart.
I think I didn't find it in time for the lecture, but
this shows the relationship between
sunspot counts, which is a good
example or a good premise for
when the sun is very active. You
can kind of see here how these
occur out of phase with each other.
So one goes up, the other goes down, vice versa.
So you're really not protected either way,
but it's mostly those protons that have
the high energies that affect us by GCRs.
Solar UV radiation. I would definitely know
the energy sources, and you did a
homework problem where you calculated the number of photons that could
break a carbon-carbon bond. I would
be familiar with that. I would also be familiar with
atmospheric transmittance or atmospheric windows.
When energy is blocked, this would be more radio waves.
So we have radio waves traveling all over the place. It's not blocked.
Good for us that a lot of the visible range is not blocked, so we can
see. But if you're around,
let's see, that would be 200 micrometers,
you would not get a whole lot of energy from that range.
The vacuum environment we know gets very
thin
as we even go up to 400 kilometers.
We also know it causes problems with heat transfer, solar
UV degradation, outgassing, and cold welding.
We talked about all that.
Heat transfer, we have severe thermal cycles.
We did an exercise in class and on the homework where
you had to calculate the
equilibrium temperature of a satellite and had to
determine appropriate thermal
protection or thermal control system
solutions to solve those problems.
So I would be familiar with that.
These are the direct inputs, and remember,
internally generated heat
counts.
This is how you calculate them for albedo
and IR. That depends on the sun angle,
and I have defined that here.
Solar UV degradation, we said can degrade
surfaces. We looked into
this, and I think I already mentioned it, carbon-carbon, what can break a
bond. We talked about contamination.
You created this
plot as part of your homework solution.
Cold welding can happen. We just need to make sure
to
account for that and to use
materials in between, coatings, adhesives, that
sort of thing, so that it doesn't occur.
Vacuum environment can cause hypoxia for humans,
but also recap it on, like we already talked about on space
systems. You can also get too much oxygen.
So that's kind of an important consideration. And make sure your hands...
If it showed the same hand, it would be all swelled up and blue too.
But it would be swelled up. So you have to carefully
maintain what
the pressure is in any human
environment and the air quality.
Vacuum environment, this is a summary of that.
Neutral environment, we discovered that it was anything but
neutral.
Drag, atomic oxygen, sputtering, spacecraft glow, and human
reentry.
Aerodynamic drag is a big deal, especially
since density is dependent on the solar cycle,
which we are in right now,
coming to the end of it here pretty soon.
We discovered the, or talked about
the layers in the Earth's atmosphere, where most
satellites fly in either the thermosphere
or the exosphere.
Aerodynamic forces, so this is how we defined
it in astro or space sciences.
We define an alternate
measure called ballistic coefficients. Let me see where that is.
I thought I had a slide on that. Maybe not.
Okay.
So we also defined a ballistic coefficient.
Ballistic coefficient is M over CDA,
which is opposite. So for streamlined,
BC would be large.
For blunt,
BC would be low. Streamlined we would want to
use for things like missiles. We don't really care about the temperature.
Blunt we would like to use for human reentry, for
example, or anything that cannot tolerate
a large thermal increase during reentry.
And then you did an in-class... No, you did a homework
problem showing how atmospheric drag affects the
satellite at a 400-kilometer altitude,
and you found that it was
like that.
Hopefully, something like that. I would be
familiar with how we calculated that and how we
came up with those equations that we did, solving for the energy of the
satellite.
Drag effects, we also discovered that
potential energy goes down,
total energy goes down, kinetic energy actually
goes up.
Semimajor axis goes down, and eccentricity
gets more circular or goes down.
Already did that. Atomic oxygen, I'd be familiar with where
you get it, reaction efficiencies, atomic oxygen flux, and
how to determine the mass loss from that.
Physical sputtering, not a whole lot there.
Spacecraft glow, not going to have anything on the final on that
that's not conceptual.
So that's quantifying those effects.
Guidelines to minimize degradation are these.
Oh, this is where I had the high ballistic coefficient.
I should have put that earlier. Anyway, we already talked about this.
And then a summary of the neutral environment.
And then I have
one more set of slides to go through quickly.
These are also review slides, so I have posted
these. I would have these review slides handy because they
summarize most of the key equations you're going to have
on The final.
Not all of them,
but a lot of them.
Okay, last section.
Space environment, part two. All right.
So charged particles and plasma, we already know where plasma comes from.
Van Allen radiation belts is a significant thing.
These are plasma densities, and I would be familiar with how to read these
charts.
Worst case in general would be during the
day during solar max, obviously. So
make sure you know how to read these.
Plasma density at higher altitudes between these two, you should be
able to find any plasma density that you need.
Please do not look up plasma densities on the Internet because you're not
approved to use the Internet on the final
exam. We talked about plasma frequencies of
oscillation. Here is
the frequencies. Again, you can use the plasma
density from these two charts. Make sure you use
8.969. Don't use nine like
Tribble does.
Don't round it off that much.
Spacecraft charging, I would know this
conceptually as well as
numerically. We did a
exercise on the homework to calculate the
mean and average speed and the voltage bias.
I would be familiar with those equations.
Some of the other problems with the
plasma environment.
Radiation environment we just covered today, so I'm not going to go into
this a whole lot
other than to say that four main disturbances.
I'm not going to ask you about anything other than solar radiation pressure on the
final. I'm not going to ask you about gravity gradient or magnetic field,
although aerodynamic would be fair game because we covered that earlier
in this summer.
Make sure that when you are calculating your reaction wheel
torque, you add in the 25% margin
factor.
These are the four effects.
Again, for the
project, you got to worry about all four, but for the final,
those are the two main ones I'd focus on.
And then we already did
that. Orbital debris, that was a fascinating
subject. I think there's a lot there that
really needs to be considered by our nation, the world
in general,
to make sure that we don't continue worsening that problem.
Some things, we might not have talked about this all in the lectures,
so I'll go over these briefly. Enhance
protection by using stronger
materials or shielding. These were what we called
Whipple shields,
and I think you even had to design the thickness of one.
Reduce the area of vulnerable surfaces.
So if you have a camera that's really important, don't point it towards
the ram side. Relocate critical items.
Again, put those where they're less susceptible. Compartmentalize.
So if something gets impacted, make sure it's compartmentalized so
that it doesn't go throughout the entire
spacecraft and damage everything.
Redundancy, of course, is always good if you can afford it.
Automatic isolation. If you get
a event in one area, isolate that
area so that it cannot harm other components.
Avoid orbits with large amounts of orbital debris.
That's a no-brainer, but there's really sometimes not anything you can
do about that. And then going into space mode
or safe mode.
So regardless of what you do,
vacuum doesn't matter. It's going to affect everyone.
Neutral and the drag
environment, neutral affects low Earth orbits,
but also look at the geo effects. So
regardless of where you are, you're going to have to worry about the space
environment.
Bio readings, I'd be familiar with all of it,
what was provided anyway and some of that.
Although,
I put a lot of that on the midterm, so I would not expect
a lot of bioastronautics on the final.
Final logistics, it'll be two and a half hours, 11
questions. I am going to release it
on...
Probably, I might even release it tonight.
I'm going to release it soon,
asking for you to sign up for a time period just like we did
for the midterm, and you'll sign
up for it. You'll have two and a half hours to return it to the
Dropbox.
If you want a breakdown of what's going to be on it, here it is.
I'm not going to write this down, but it's being recorded, so you can go back over
it. Problem one is true/false, like it was on the midterm.
Problem two is multiple choice, like it was on the midterm.
Problem three will be an atmospheric windows and
sun or sun irradiance question.
Problem four will be on plasma. Problem five,
radiation. Problem six, plasma.
Problem seven, overall space hazards.
Problem eight, communication. Problem nine,
thermal
control or thermal analysis and design.
Problem 10, MMOD, and then
problem 11 will be on the neutral environment
and some of the work we did leading up to that.
Okay, final project. Some things that I am looking for, and I
will write these down.
For a
formal project, of course, you will have a cover page.
I've been requiring that since the beginning,
but some of you have been providing this, some of you haven't.
Have an abstract for a formal report, and this is for the
final project, not for
milestone two. I will grade
milestone two as I have it provided in the rubric.
Nomenclature goes next.
That may take a significant amount of time if you
haven't been doing that already. You would have intro,
body, of course, talking about all the work you did in the
milestones, conclusions.
And a couple of other notes that I want to make.
This is a formal report, so I would expect
formal writing, which includes do not use
contractions, don't use first or second
person.
Include figures and equations and number
them. Number them and refer to them.
Have an appendix and refer to your appendix.
And that's all I have for tonight. We got four minutes to spare.
Are there any questions about anything?
Okay.
Three minutes to spare now. All right.
So, won't see you next week. This was the
last lecture. I will post information about the final here
pretty soon. I've already posted information about the final
project and the final homework. I think
you've got plenty to work on. Plus, I got a lot of grading to do
between now and the formal end of the
semester, which is August
9th?
Yeah, August 9th. I got to get grade in by Tuesday, so
please do not be late with anything because I'm going to dedicate
mostly Monday to
grading.
Okay. Have a great night.
Thank you.
Thanks.